Guide to the John Breon Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Breon papers
1936-1984
1944-1951
YCAL MSS 1
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9
(17 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, diaries, writings, subject files, and personal papers of John Breon concerning his World War II experiences, correspondents include Pat Carroll, Charles Cerbone, Gertrude Stein, Alice B. Toklas, and Carl Van Vechten.
Other Storage Formats: Oversize
Breon, John Wallace, 1923-1984
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The material was donated to The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in 1986 by Charles Cerbone, a longtime friend of Breon's, and Margaret Buxton, whose husband, John, was Breon's third cousin.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 16: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
JOHN WALLACE BREON, JR. (1923-1984)
John Breon was born in Rockford, Illinois, on August 21, 1923, the son of John Wallace Breon and Jessie Breon. He served in the infantry in France during World War II, at which time he met Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas. After his discharge from the army, he studied in Paris. In 1946 Breon returned to the United States and entered Beloit College. After his graduation in 1949, he spent two years at the Sorbonne and at the University of Florence. While in Italy, he began work on a novel, The Sorrows of Travel (1955), a copy of which can be found in the Beinecke printed collection.
During the 1950s Breon joined McGraw-Hill Company. but in 1966 he left McGraw-Hill for the New American Library. He remained with the NAL until 1968, when he took a position with Franklin Speir, Inc., a New York advertising agency. In 1969 he returned to McGraw-Hill, joining the Industrial and Business Books Division as an advertising copywriter. Breon retired in 1979.
In 1963 Breon and a companion, Charles Cerbone, purchased the Ryerson House in Wayne, New Jersey. In 1982 they moved to Succasunna, New Jersey, where John Breon died after a lengthy illness on April 21, 1984.
Scope and Contents
The John Breon Papers document the life of the editor and writer John Wallace Breon, Jr. The papers span the dates 1936-1984, with a large part of the material covering the years 1944-1951.
The collection has three series. Series I, Correspondence, Boxes 1-8, consists of letters between John Breon and his family and friends. Series II, Diaries, contains the diaries of John Breon and is housed in Boxes 9-10. Series III, Personal Papers, is housed in Boxes 11-14.
Series I, Correspondence, is composed of alphabetically arranged correspondence spanning the years 1944-84. Breon's letters to his family document his military and academic career between 1944-1951, while correspondence to his friends concerns his varied interests and activities in later years.
The 1944 correspondence details Breon's basic army training at Camp Shelby, Mississippi (Box 1, folders 2-8) and includes his impressions of officers and enlisted men. He also discusses his daily activities, provides diagrams of bivouac problems, and outlines his code school training. At the end of 1944 Breon was sent overseas.
With the war drawing to a close in the spring of 1945 and restrictions on correspondence being lifted, Breon was able to write more freely on such matters as conditions in war-torn Germany, the German people, and refugees. He also wrote a long and detailed account of his trip from Camp Shelby to England and his experiences in the British Isles, France, Belgium, and Germany (Box 2, Folders 29-37).
In October 1945 Breon went to Paris on leave and met Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas (Box 2, folder 34-35). He discusses their initial conversation, their thoughts on the German occupation of France, the theme of "choice" in Gertrude Stein's upcoming work, her dislike of Ernest Hemingway, and Breon's education and writing career.
In November 1945 Breon was transferred to the French Institute of Motion Pictures. His letters describe Paris immediately following the war, including the illumination of the city for the first time since the occupation. He writes about his study of French movie techniques, his social life, the ballet, and his holiday in Mont St. Michel. He also writes in considerable detail about the people he met, including Marlene Dietrich, the actor, Jean Gabin,the stage designer, Christian Berard, and Jean Cocteau, as well as Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas (Box 3-4, folders 36-60). With Stein's help he was admitted to the Sorbonne and he describes his classes, fellow students, and professors. In July 1946 Breon was discharged and returned to the United States.
Breon resumed his studies in Europe in September 1949. He chronicles his transatlantic crossing, his reunion with Alice B. Toklas, his impressions of Rome while on holiday there with Carl Van Vechten, his daily activities, his friends, and the general mood of Paris in the late 1940s. He also wrote about giving English lessons to Dora Maar, Picasso's mistress in the late 1930s and early 1940s; his introduction to Thornton Wilder by Alice B. Toklas; and the novel he had begun writing in the summer of 1950. Upon completion of his studies Breon took a job with the State Department in Paris and he recorded his impressions of the job and his co-workers.
Breon also maintained a lengthy correspondence with Margaret Buxton from 1959-84 (Box 5, folders 84-98). His letters to her provide considerable detail about the Ryerson House, the eighteenth-century dwelling Breon purchased with his companion Charles Cerbone in the early 1960s. Other topics include the decoration of the house, the genealogical history of the Breon family, books, antiques, Gertrude Stein, and a play Breon was writing, "See Grady See."
The papers contain a large number of letters from Pat Carroll, the star of the play "Gertrude Stein, Gertrude Stein, Gertrude Stein," (Boxes 5-7, folders 100-124). The letters are primarily concerned with the play, although some discussion of family news is included. There are also letters from Mary Ellen Devery, the producer of "Gertrude Stein, Gertrude Stein, Gertrude Stein," containing news of the play and Pat Carroll (Box 7, folders 135-137).
Other correspondents include Dora Maar, Clement Richer, Samuel Seward, and Norman Mailer, who offered criticism of Breon's published novel, The Sorrows of Travel. Breon's correspondence with Gertrude Stein can be found in the Gertrude Stein Papers. His correspondence with Carl Van Vechten is located in the Carl Van Vechten Papers. Photocopies of these letters are in Box 8, folders 163, and 166- 167.
Series II, Diaries, is housed in Boxes 9-10. The diaries span the years 1949-84 and are arranged chronologically. The diaries for the years 1949-51 complement the correspondence of the same period.
The 1949 diary begins while Breon was still attending college in Rockford, Illinois. It contains details on Rockford, his friends, his feelings about leaving college, and his short stay in New York. Breon describes his voyage to Europe, comments on his fellow passengers, and reflects on leaving Rockford and returning to Paris. He also recorded his reunion with Alice B. Toklas, including their discussion concerning the publication of Stein manuscripts. He chronicles their efforts to assist Bernard Fäy with his legal problems, comments on Olga Picasso's relationship with Picasso, and records Alice B. Toklas's account of Gertrude Stein's meeting with James Joyce. Breon describes his holiday in Rome with Carl Van Vechten. The 1949-51 diaries provide a record of Breon's friendships and social activities and include wide ranging personal reflections.
Breon's diaries for the years 1952-59 deal with family problems; his father's death; unemployment; his unpublished novel, The Separation Center; reflections on his state of mind and his relationships with friends. The diaries spanning the years 1960-84 are much less detailed than those of earlier years. Breon reflects on his youth, personal relationships with others, his difficulties with McGraw-Hill, the death of his mother, and health problems. The diaries end approximately one month before his death.
Series III, Personal Papers, can be found in Boxes 11-14. Included in this series are art exhibit catalogues, drawings by Maurice Genis, and material pertaining to the artist Alfonso Ossario. Breon kept clippings on subjects which interested him for example, Gertrude Stein, Alice B. Toklas, and Carl Van Vechten.
The photographs, (Box 12, folders 214-216), are primarily of art works and include a portrait of John Breon by Rudolphe Schneider and works of art by Alfonso Ossario. Series III also contains a photocopy of the second draft of "See Grady See," a play Breon wrote in the late 1970s and frequently revised. The play is an experimental one, based upon the experiences of friends. Military papers consist of material relating to Breon's military service (Box 12, folders 207-209). The collection also contains medical records, papers on his retirement, material on the history of the Ryerson House, and advertising copy written for McGraw-Hill.
Basic training (Military education); Friendship; Single men; Diaries -- United States; Breon family; Breon, John Wallace, 1923-1984; Burton, Margaret; Carroll, Pat, 1927-; Cerbone, Charles; Devery, Mary Ellen; Dregon, Edward F.; Genis, Maurice; Maar, Dora, 1907-1997; Ossario, Alfonso; Richer, Clément; Ryerson, Edward L.; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Toklas, Alice Babette, 1877-1967; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; United States. Army ( Military life)
- Correspondence, 1944-1984; Series I; 4.00' (8 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence consists of eight boxes of alphabetically arranged correspondence. All material is arranged in chronological order within each folder. Individuals are given separate listings based on their importance in the collection or provided the file contains six or more items. The correspondence of those who appear one to five times is filed alphabetically with the first letter of the surname in "Letter" general files.
  - "B" general, 1945-73, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Breon, John, 1944 Mar-1945 Jun (Box 1, Folder 2-22)
  - Breon, John, 1945 Jul-1945 Nov (Box 2, Folder 23-37)
  - Breon, John, 1945 Nov-1946 Mar (Box 3, Folder 38-54)
  - Breon, John, 1946 Mar-1984 (Box 4, Folder 55-82)
  - Burns, Edward, 1973-80 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Buxton, Margaret, 1959-84 (Box 5, Folder 84-98)
  - "C" general, 1983, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Carroll, Pat, 1980 Jan-May (Box 5, Folder 100-01)
  - Carroll, Pat, 1980 Jun-1984 Feb (Box 6, Folder 102-23)
  - Carroll, Pat, 1984 Mar-Apr (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Cerbone, Charles, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 125-32)
  - Coccioli, Carlo, 1950-83 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - "D" general, 1951-80 (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - Devery, Mary Ellen, 1980-83 (Box 7, Folder 135-37)
  - Diesbach, Ghislain de, 1977-84 (Box 7, Folder 138)
  - Dragon, Edward F., 1958-81 (Box 7, Folder 139-40)
  - "F" general, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - "G" general, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Gallup, Donald, 1952-84 (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - Genis, Maurice, 1950-66, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 144-46)
  - Guyenot, Pierre, 1957-68, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 147)
  - "H" general, 1974, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 148)
  - "J" general, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 149)
  - "K" general, 1946-62 (Box 8, Folder 150)
  - "L" general, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 151)
  - "M" general, 1959-75 (Box 8, Folder 152)
  - Maar, Dora, 1950-73 (Box 8, Folder 153)
  - Mailer, Norman, 1955-56 (Box 8, Folder 154)
  - "O" general, 1955-80 (Box 8, Folder 155)
  - "P" general, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 156)
  - "R" general, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 157)
  - Reynolds, Charlie, 1973-74 (Box 8, Folder 158)
  - Richer, Clement, 1950-60, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 159)
  - Ryerson, Edward, 1965-68 (Box 8, Folder 160-61)
  - "S" general, 1960-84 (Box 8, Folder 162)
  - Stein, Gertrude, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 163)
    Includes: ALS from Stein to Breon's mother
  - Steward, Samuel, 1977-82 (Box 8, Folder 164)
  - "T" general, 1964-84 (Box 8, Folder 165)
  - Toklas, Alice B., 1946-62 (Box 8a, Folder 166a-d)
    Includes: ALS from Toklas to Breon's mother
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1949-64, n.d. (Box 8a, Folder 167-69)
  - "W" general, 1981 (Box 8a, Folder 170)
  - Yale University Library, 1957-84 (Box 8a, Folder 171)
  - "Z" general, 1960 (Box 8a, Folder 172)
  - Unidentified, 1972-84, n.d. (Box 8a, Folder 173)
- Diaries, 1949-1984; Series II; 1.00' (2 boxes)
  Series II, Diaries, is composed of two boxes of chronologically arranged material.
  - Diary, 1949 Apr-Dec (Box 9, Folder 174)
  - Diary, 1949 Dec-1951 Apr (Box 9, Folder 175)
  - Diary, 1951 May-1953 Feb (Box 9, Folder 176)
  - Diary, 1953 Apr-Dec (Box 9, Folder 177)
  - Diary, 1954 Jan-1955 Apr (Box 9, Folder 178)
  - Diary, 1955 Apr-1956 May (Box 9, Folder 179)
  - Diary, 1956 May-1957 Aug (Box 9, Folder 180)
  - Diary, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 181)
  - Diary, 1959 Feb-1965 Apr (Box 10, Folder 182)
  - Diary, 1965 Jun-1968 Mar (Box 10, Folder 183)
  - Diary, 1968 Apr-1978 Dec (Box 10, Folder 184)
  - Diary, 1979 Jun-1984 Mar (Box 10, Folder 185)
- Personal Papers, 1936-1984; Series III; 3.50' (5 boxes)
  The papers in Series III are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Art exhibit catalogues, 1949-69 (Box 11, Folder 186)
  - Cocteau, Jean
    - Drawings, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 187)
  - Education, 1943-51 (Box 11, Folder 188)
  - Gallup, Donald, 1980, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 189)
  - Genet, Jean
    - Querell de Brest, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 190)
  - Genis, Maurice, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 191)
  - "Gertrude Stein, Gertrude Stein, Gertrude Stein", 1980-81 (Box 11, Folder 192-93)
  - Internal Revenue Service, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 194)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1967-79, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 195-98)
  - Medical bills, 1980-82 (Box 11, Folder 199-201)
  - Medical bills, 1983-84, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 202-206)
  - Military papers, 1944-84, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 207-209)
  - Miscellaneous, 1949-84, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 210-13)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Oversize, Box 15, folder 246
  - Photographs
    - Breon, John, ca. 1946, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 214)
    - Miscellaneous, 1945, n.d.] (Box 12, Folder 215)
    - Ossario, Alfonso, 1942-76, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 216)
      See also: Oversize, Box 15, folder 247
    - Ossario, Alfonso, 1947-82 (Box 13, Folder 217-18)
  - Postcards, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 219)
  - Resumé, ca. 1979 (Box 13, Folder 220)
  - Retirement, 1980-83 (Box 13, Folder 221-22)
  - Ryerson House, 1938-82, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 223)
  - Stein, Gertrude
    See also: Oversize, Box 15, folder 248
    - Art, 1967-71 (Box 13, Folder 224)
    - A Book Concluding With a Wife Has A Cow, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 225)
    - Biographical, 1943-64 (Box 13, Folder 226)
    - Book reviews, 1943-64 (Box 13, Folder 227)
    - On Our Way, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 228)
    - Writings, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 229)
  - Theater programs, 1939, 1952, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 230)
  - Toklas, Alice B., 1967-72, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 231-32)
  - Writings
    - I Hardly Know What to do About Christmas Some Years Ago, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 233)
    - "See Grady See", ca. 1977 (Box 14, Folder 234-40)
    - Vingt Lithographs pour un libre que jài lu, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 241)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1964-84 (Box 14, Folder 242)
  - Verlaine, Paul
    - Oeuvre Libres, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 243)
  - Unemployment, 1976-80, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 244)
  - Yale University Library, 1974-75 (Box 14, Folder 245)
- Oversize
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15 (Oversize), Folder 246)
  - Photographs: Alfonso Ossario (Box 15 (Oversize), Folder 247)
  - Stein, Gertrude: scrapbooks, 1945-52 (Box 15 (Oversize), Folder 248)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.50' (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folders 7, 9, 15, 17-22 (Box 16, Folder 249)
  - Box 2, folders 23-27, 29-31, 34-36 (Box 16, Folder 250-51)
  - Box 3, folders 39, 44-45, 48-49, 51, 53 (Box 16, Folder 252)
  - Box 4, folders 56-59, 64,78, 81 (Box 16, Folder 253)
  - Box 5, folders 84-88, 90, 92, 94-96 (Box 16, Folder 254)
  - Box 7, folders 133-34 (Box 16, Folder 255)
  - Box 8, folders 144, 149-50, 152, 160, 162, 165 (Box 16, Folder 256)
  - Box 10, folder 184 (Box 16, Folder 257)
  - Box 11, folders 189, 191-92 (Box 16, Folder 258)
  - Box 12, folders 209, 211 (Box 16, Folder 259)
  - Box 13, folders 218, 223-24, 226-27 (Box 16, Folder 260)
  - Box 14, folders 231, 242 (Box 16, Folder 261)